<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?latexml searchpaths="/mnt/c/Users/Jordan/Documents/GitHub/LaTeX/historical/predicates"?>
<?latexml class="article"?>
<?latexml package="amsmath,amssymb,mathrsfs,amsthm,xfrac"?>
<?latexml package="fontenc" options="LGR,T1"?>
<?latexml RelaxNGSchema="LaTeXML"?>
<document xmlns="http://dlmf.nist.gov/LaTeXML" class="ltx_authors_1line">
  <resource src="LaTeXML.css" type="text/css"/>
  <resource src="ltx-article.css" type="text/css"/>
  <title>Predicates</title>
  <creator role="author">
    <personname>Jordan Bell</personname>
  </creator>
  <date role="creation">March 4, 2017</date>
  <para xml:id="p1">
    <p><text font="italic">totus</text>: whole, <text font="italic">omnis</text>: all, <text font="italic">quisque</text>: every/each, <text font="italic">quisquam</text>: any, <text font="italic">cuncta</text>, <text font="italic">singulis</text></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p2">
    <p>Latin, Spevak <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="spevak" separator="," yyseparator=","/>]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p3">
    <p>Bourbaki style the folloiwng are equivalent</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p4">
    <p>Fréchet space defined as such, or as limit of Banach spaces. Fréchet space: genus topological vector space, difference
topology is induced by countably family of seminorms and with induced metric it is a complete metric space.</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p5">
    <p>Porphyry, <text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>]</cite>:
genus, difference, species, property, accident.
Three uses of the word genus: first, “The genus of the Heraclids is so called in this meaning, from their relation to some one item–I mean, to Hercules–, the plurality of people somehow related to one another taking their name, in contradistinction to the other genera, from the affinity derived from him.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 3, §1]</cite>
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣25␣**** -->Second, “Again, in another sense we call a genus the origin of anyone’s birth, whether from his progenitor or from the place in which he was born.”
Third, “Again, in another sense we call a genus that under which a species is ordered, no doubt in virtue of a similarity with the former cases; for such a genus is a sort of origin for the items under it, and a plurality is held to contain everything under it.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 4, §1]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p6">
    <p>X is predicated of a genus as a genus if and only if it is true of every member of the genus.</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p7">
    <p>“Thus genera are so called in three ways; and it is the third which is of account to philosophers. Delineating it, they present it by saying that a genus is what is predicated, in answer to ‘What is it?’, of several items which differ in species; for example, animal.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 4, §1]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p8">
    <p>delineate=upographein</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p9">
    <p>“differ in number”: items differ in number if they are distinct, <text font="italic">Met</text> 1016b31–35</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p10">
    <p>Porphyry, <text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 4–5, §2]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p11">
    <quote>
      <p>Genera differ from what is predicated of only one item in that they are predicated of several items. Again, they differ from what is predicated of several items–from species because species, even if they are predicated of several items, are predicated of items which differ not in species but in number. Thus man, being a species, is predicated of Socrates and of Plato, who differ from one another not in species but in number, whereas animal, being a genus, is predicated of man and of cow and of horse, which differ from one another not only in number but also in species. Again, a genus differs from a property because a property is predicated of only one species–the species of which it is a property– and of the individuals under the species (as laughing is predicated only of man, and of particular men), whereas a genus is predicated not of one species but of several which differ. Again, a genus differs from a
difference and from common accidents because differences and common accidents, even if they are predicated of several items which differ in species, are not predicated of them in answer to ‘What is it?’ but rather to ‘What sort of so-and-so is it?’. Asked what sort of so-and-so a man
is, we say that he is rational; and asked what sort of so-and-so a raven is, we say that it is black–rational is a difference, black an accident. But when we are asked what a man is, we answer an animal–and animal is a genus of man.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p12">
    <p><text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 6, §2]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p13">
    <quote>
      <p>What I mean should become clear in the case of a single type of predication. Substance is itself a genus. Under it is body, and under body animate body, under which is animal; under
animal is rational animal, under which is man; and under man are Socrates and Plato and particular men. Of these items, substance is the most general and is only a genus, while man is
the most special and is only a species. Body is a species of substance and a genus of animate body. Animate body is a species of body and a genus of animal. Again, animal is a species
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣50␣**** -->of animate body and a genus of rational animal. Rational animal is a species of animal and a genus of man. Man is a species of rational animal, but not a genus of particular men–only a species.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p14">
    <p>Porphyry, <text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 7, §2]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p15">
    <quote>
      <p>The most general items, then, are ten; the most special are of a certain number, but not an infinite one; the individuals–that is to say, the items after the most special items–are infinite.
That is why Plato advised those who descend from the most general items to the most special to stop there, and to descend through the intermediates, dividing them by the specific differences; and he tells us to leave the infinites alone, for there will be no knowledge of them. So, when we are descending to the most special items, it is necessary to divide and to
proceed through a plurality, and when we are ascending to the most general items, it is necessary to bring the plurality together. For species–and still more, genera–gather the many
items into a single nature; whereas the particulars or singulars, in contrary fashion, always divide the one into a plurality. For by sharing in the species the many men are one man, and by the particulars the one and common man is several–for the singular is always divisive whereas the common is collective and unificatory.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p16">
    <p><text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 7–8, §2]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p17">
    <quote>
      <p>Genera and species–what each of them is–having been presented, and the genus being one whereas the species are several (for the splitting of a genus always yields several species), the genus is always predicated of the species (and all the upper items of the lower items), but a species is predicated neither of its proximate genus nor of the upper items–for it does not convert. For it must be the case that either equals are predicated of equals (as neighing of horse) or the larger of the
smaller (as animal of man); but not the smaller of the larger–you will not say that animal is a man as you will say that man is an animal.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p18">
    <p><text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 8, §2]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p19">
    <quote>
      <p>Of whatever a species is predicated, of those items, by necessity, will the genus of the species also be predicated–and the genus of the genus as far as the most general item. For if it is true to say that Socrates is a man, man is an animal, and animal is a substance, then it is also true to say that Socrates is an animal and a substance. For, the upper items being always predicated of the lower, a species will be predicated of the individual, a genus both of the species and of the individual, and a most general item both of the genus (or of the genera, should there be several intermediate and subaltern items) and of the species and of the individual. For a most general item is said of everything under it–genera and species and individuals; a genus which comes before a most special item is said of all the most special items and of the individuals; an item which is only a species is said of all the individuals; and an individual is said of one only of the particulars.
<break/>
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣75␣**** -->Socrates is said to be an individual, and so are this white thing, and this person approaching, and the son of Sophroniscus (should Socrates be his only son). Such items are called individuals because each is constituted of proper features the assemblage of which will never be found the same in anything else–the proper features of Socrates will never be found in any other of the particulars. On the other hand, the proper features of man (I mean, of the common man) will be found the same in several items–or rather, in all particular men in so far as they are men.
<break/>
Thus an individual is contained by the species and a species by the genus. For a genus is a sort of whole, an individual a part, and a species both a whole and a part–but a part of one thing and a whole (not of another item but) in other items (for a whole is in the parts).</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p20">
    <p><text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 8–9, §3]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p21">
    <quote>
      <p>Let differences be so called commonly, properly, and most properly. For one item is said to differ commonly from a diverse item when it is distinguished in any fashion by a diversity either in relation to itself or
in relation to another item–Socrates differs from Plato by diversity, and indeed from himself as a boy and as a grown man, and as being active in some way or having stopped, and always in respect of diversities in what he is like. One item is said to differ properly from a diverse item when it differs from it by an inseparable accident–inseparable accidents are, for example, blue-eyedness or hook-nosedness or even a hardened scar from a wound. One item is said to differ most properly from a diverse item when it is distinguished by a specific difference–as man differs from horse by a specific difference, that of rational.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p22">
    <p><text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 12, §4]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p23">
    <quote>
      <p>For even if man does not always laugh, he is said to be laughing not in that he always laughs but in that he is of such a nature as to laugh–and this holds of him always, being connatural, like neighing of horses. And they say that these are properties in the strict sense, because they convert: if horse, neighing; and if neighing, horse.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p24">
    <p><text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 15, §9]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p25">
    <quote>
      <p>Again, if properties are removed they do not co-remove the genera; but if genera are removed, they co-remove the species to which the properties belong, so that, that of which they are properties being removed, the properties themselves are also co-removed.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p26">
    <p><text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 16, §11]</cite>:
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣100␣**** --></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p27">
    <quote>
      <p>Common to difference and species is the fact that they are participated in equally: particular men participate equally in man and also in the difference of rational.
<break/>
Also common to them is the fact that they are always present in what participates in them; for Socrates is always rational and Socrates is always a man.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p28">
    <p><text font="italic">Metaphysics</text> 1076a32–37, problem of universals</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p29">
    <p>Macrobius IV 361 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 68]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p30">
    <quote>
      <p>A subject is a primary substance…e.g. Cicero–not the name but what is signified by the name.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p31">
    <p><text font="italic">Topics</text> 102a31–35 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 65]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p32">
    <quote>
      <p>A genus is what is predicated, in answer to ‘What is it?’, of several items which differ in species. Let things be said to be predicated in answer to ‘What is it?’ if it is appropriate to present them when asked what the item before us is–e.g. in the case of man it is appropriate, when asked what the item in question is, to say that it is an animal.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p33">
    <p>2a19: “It is clear from what has been said that if something is said of a subject both its name and its definition
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣125␣**** -->are necessarily predicated of the subject. For example, man is said of a subject, the individual man, and the name
is of course predicated (since you will be predicating man
of the individual man), and also the definition of man will be predicated of the individual man (since the individual man is also
a man). Thus both the name and the definition will be predicated of the subject.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 6]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p34">
    <p>“But as the primary substances stand to the other things, so the species stands to the genus: the species is a subject
for the genus (for the genera are predicated of the species but the species are not predicated reciprocally of the genera).”
<cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 7]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p35">
    <p>Simplicius, <text font="italic">in Cat</text> 119.26–30 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 60]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p36">
    <quote>
      <p>It should also be realized that it is not possible to give accurate definitions of the highest genera; rather, accounts of such items are more like reminders or delineations, and more must not be asked from them than they can supply. Hence for these items it is enough to give some property, from which it is possible to know what they are.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p37">
    <p><text font="italic">On Interpretation</text> 1, 16a1: “name”, “verb” (<text font="italic">verbum</text>), “negation” (<text font="italic">negatio</text>), “affirmation” (<text font="italic">affirmation</text>),
“statement” (<text font="italic">enuntiatio</text>), “sentence” (<text font="italic">oratio</text>).</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p38">
    <p>“affection
in/of the soul” (<text font="italic">anima passionum</text>),
“likeness of”, “actual things”, “symbol of”, “spoken sound”, “written mark”.
“Now spoken sounds are symbols of affections in the soul, and written marks symbols of spoken sounds. And
just as written marks are not the same for all men, neither are spoken sounds. But what these are in the first
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣150␣**** -->place signs of – affections of the soul – are the same for all; and what these affections are likenesses of – actual things –
are also the same.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 43]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p39">
    <p>“Just as some thoughts in the soul are neither true
nor false while some are necessarily one or the other, so
also with spoken sounds. For falsity and truth have to do
with combination and separation. Thus names and verbs
by themselves – for instance ‘man’ or ‘white’ when nothing
further is added – are like the thoughts that are without
combination and separation; for so far they are neither
true nor false. A sign of this is that even ‘goat-stag’ signifies
something but not, as yet, anything true or false – unless
‘is’ or ‘is not’ is added (either simply or with reference to
time).” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 43]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p40">
    <p>2, 16a19: “A <text font="italic">name</text> is a spoken sound significant by convention,
without time, none of whose parts is significant in separation.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 43]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p41">
    <p>3, 16b6: “A <text font="italic">verb</text> is what additionally signifies time, no part
of it being significant separately; and it is a sign of things
said of something else.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 44]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p42">
    <p>16b8: “It additionally signifies time: ‘recovery’ is a name,
but ‘recovers’ is a verb, because it additionally signifies
something’s holding <text font="italic">now</text>. And it is always a sign of what
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣175␣**** -->holds, that is, holds of a subject.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 44]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p43">
    <p>4, 16b26: “A <text font="italic">sentence</text> is a significant spoken sound some part
of which is significant in separation – as an expression,
not as an affirmation.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 45]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p44">
    <p>16b33: “Every sentence is significant (not as a tool, but,
as we said, by convention), but not every sentence is a
statement-making sentence, but only those in which there
is truth or falsity.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 45]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p45">
    <p>17a2–3 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="barnes" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 3]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p46">
    <quote>
      <p>not every saying is assertoric – only those in which being true or being false holds.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p47">
    <p>5, 17a23: “The simple statement is a significant spoke sound
about whether something does or does not hold (in one
of the divisions of time).” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 46]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p48">
    <p>6, 17a25: “An <text font="italic">affirmation</text> is a statement affirming something
of something, a <text font="italic">negation</text> is a statement denying something
of something.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 47]</cite></p>
  </para>
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣200␣**** -->  <para xml:id="p49">
    <p>7, 17a38:
<cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 47]</cite> “stating universally of a universal”, e.g. “every man is white” and
“no man is white”; “stating of a universal not universally”, e.g.
“a man is white” and “a man is not white”.
“for ‘every’ does not signify the universal but that it is taken universally” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 48]</cite>.
“It is not true to predicate a universal universally of a subject, for there cannot be
an affirmation in which a universal is predicated universally of a subject,
for instance ‘every man is every animal’.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 48]</cite>
“every man is white” and “not every man is white”, affirmation and negation with
one signifies universally and the other signifies not universally,
called <text font="italic">contradictory opposites</text>;
universal affirmation and universal negation are <text font="italic">contrary opposites</text>, e.g.
“every man is just” and “no man is just”. <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 48]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p50">
    <p>9, 19a23: “I mean, for example: it is necessary for there to be or not to be
a sea-battle tomorrow; but it is not necessary for a sea-battle
to take place tomorrow, nor for one not to take place –
though it is necessary for one to take place or not
to take place.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 53]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p51">
    <p>20a3–6: gallop vs. are gallopers</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p52">
    <p>14, 24a6–9: “For if in the belief about the good that it is good ‘the good’ is taken universally,
it is the same as the belief that whatever is good is good.” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="ackrill" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 67]</cite></p>
  </para>
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣225␣**** -->  <para xml:id="p53">
    <p>Dexippus <text font="italic">in Cat</text> 10.25–32 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="barnes" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 116]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p54">
    <quote>
      <p>The predicates are not the entities themselves but the expressions which signify the thoughts and the objects.
When they say
<break/>
Animal is predicated of man
<break/>
they say that the expression significant of animal – which is the name animal – is predicated of the thought signified by the expression man and of the object which is subject to that thought; for being predicated is a property of significant utterances which signify thoughts and objects.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p55">
    <quote>
      <p>Animals are not predicated, nor are thoughts of animals or the concept of an animal: what is predicated is the word
‘animal’. But not every word can be predicated: not the word ‘blityri’, for example, because though it is a word, it has no sense; not the words ‘often’ or ‘and’ or ‘through’,
for example, because although they are words endowed with senses, they do not signify anything.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p56">
    <p>Barnes <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 69]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p57">
    <quote>
      <p>The late commentators rehearse three simple answers to the question ‘What is a predicate?’: a predicate is an expression; a predicate is a concept; a predicate is an object.
All three answers are then rejected in favour of a composite reply: Predicates are expressions insofar as they designate objects by way of concepts.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p58">
    <p>Barnes <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 70]</cite>:
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣250␣**** --></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p59">
    <quote>
      <p>The late commentators are wrong in thinking that this is a combination of their three simple views: it is the first of the three, construed in a particular way.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p60">
    <p>Dexippus, <text font="italic">in Cat</text> 14.27 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 76]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p61">
    <quote>
      <p>the predicates are words, the genera are natures</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p62">
    <p>Cicero, <text font="italic">de orat</text> I xlii 189 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 63]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p63">
    <quote>
      <p>A genus is something which embraces two or more parts, similar by a certain commonality but different in species; parts are what are subordinate to the genera from which they derive.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p64">
    <p>Dionysius Thrax, <text font="italic">Art</text> 11 [22.4-23.1] <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="barnes" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 207]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p65">
    <quote>
      <p>An expression is a smallest part of a constructed saying. A saying is a combination of prose expressions which indicates a complete thought.
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣275␣**** --></p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p66">
    <p>Dionysius Thrax 12, 24.2–6 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 315]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p67">
    <quote>
      <p>A name [<text font="italic">onoma</text>] is a part of speech which has cases and which signifies a body or an object (a body, e.g. stone; an object, e.g. education), and which is used both commonly and properly (commonly, e.g. man, horse; properly, e.g. Socrates).</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p68">
    <p>33.6–34.2:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p69">
    <quote>
      <p>A name in the strict sense is one which signifies a proper substance, e.g. Homer, Socrates; an appellative name is one which signifies a common substance, e.g. man, horse.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p70">
    <p>Dionysius Thrax 12, 43.1–44.1 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 64]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p71">
    <quote>
      <p>A general name is one which can be divided into several species, e.g. animal, plant. A special name is one which is divided from a genus, e.g. ox, horse, vine, olive-tree.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p72">
    <p>Barnes <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 319–320]</cite>: Greeks did not have inverted commas, used definite article, e.g. <text font="italic">to lege</text> means “the verb <text font="italic">lege</text>”.</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p73">
    <p>Priscian, <text font="italic">Institutiones Grammaticae</text> ii iv 15 [ii 53.28-29] <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="barnes" separator="," yyseparator=","/>]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p74">
    <quote>
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣300␣**** -->      <p>A saying is a sequence of expressions which is well formed and which indicates a complete thought.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p75">
    <p>Apollonius Dyscolus, <text font="italic">Syntax</text> i 1 [1.1-2.2] <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="barnes" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 208]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p76">
    <quote>
      <p>In the lectures which we have already made public an account of utterances was laid out as the matter demanded. The publication which is now to be presented will contain the construction of utterances into well-formed and complete sayings, a matter which I have decided to set out with all exactitude inasmuch as it is indispensable for the interpretation of poetry.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p77">
    <p>Apollonius Dyscolus, <text font="italic">On Conjunctions</text> 225.9–10 <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="barnes" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 208]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p78">
    <quote>
      <p>‘It is day’ is complete, but ‘Either it is day’ is not complete.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p79">
    <p>saying=complete saying=sentence</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p80">
    <p>Donatus, <text font="italic">Ars minor</text></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p81">
    <p>Priscian, <text font="italic">Institutiones grammaticae</text></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p82">
    <p>Martianus Capella, <text font="italic">The Marriage of Philology and Mercury</text> IV (Dialectic) <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="capellaII" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 112]</cite>:
[344] “<text font="italic">Genus</text> is the embracing of many forms by means of a single name”. For example, <text font="italic">animal</text>,
which has the forms <text font="italic">man</text>, <text font="italic">horse</text>, <text font="italic">lion</text>, etc. And the genus <text font="italic">man</text> is a form in relation to
<text font="italic">animal</text> and a genus to <text font="italic">barbarian</text> and <text font="italic">Roman</text>.
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣325␣**** -->“Genus can extend right down to the point where on dividing it into its forms
you reach the individual.” For example, divide <text font="italic">men</text> into <text font="italic">males</text> and <text font="italic">females</text>;
divide <text font="italic">males</text> into <text font="italic">boys</text>, <text font="italic">youths</text>, and <text font="italic">old men</text>; divide
<text font="italic">boys</text> into <text font="italic">infants</text> and <text font="italic">those who can speak</text>.
“If you wished to divide <text font="italic">boy</text> into <text font="italic">Ganymede</text> or some other particular boy,
that is not a genus, because you have arrived at the individual.”
“We ought to use the genus which is closest to the matter in
hand, so that if we are discussing <text font="italic">man</text>, we ought to take <text font="italic">animal</text> as
the genus because it is closest to our subject. For if we take as our
genus <text font="italic">substance</text>, that is true in logic but is too wide for our needs.”</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p83">
    <p>Sections 344–54 correspond to Porphyry, <text font="italic">Isagoge</text>, on the <text font="italic">quinque voces</text>, “five terms”, “five predicables”.</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p84">
    <p><text font="italic">logica vetus</text>: <text font="italic">Categories</text> and <text font="italic">On Interpretation</text>; Porphyry, <text font="italic">Isagoge</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="isagoge" separator="," yyseparator=","/>]</cite>; Boethius, <text font="italic">De topicis differentiis</text>,
<text font="italic">De divisione</text>, <text font="italic">De syllogismis categoricis</text>, <text font="italic">De syllogismis hypotheticis</text>; <text font="italic">Liber sex principiorum</text>; Cicero, <text font="italic">Topica</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="reinhardt" separator="," yyseparator=","/>]</cite>.</p>
  </para>
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣350␣**** -->  <para xml:id="p85">
    <p><text font="italic">logica nova</text>: <text font="italic">Prior Analytics</text>, <text font="italic">Posterior Analytics</text>, <text font="italic">Topics</text>, <text font="italic">Sophistical Refutations</text></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p86">
    <p><text font="italic">logica moderna</text>: terminist logic, categorematic and syncategorematic terms, supposition (material, personal, simple),</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p87">
    <p>Peter Abelard</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p88">
    <p>token, type</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p89">
    <p><text font="italic">Topicaa</text></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p90">
    <p>Abelard, <text font="italic">Dialectica</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="dialectica" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 153]</cite>, <text font="italic">propositio</text> (propositional sign) is an <text font="italic">oratio verum falsumve significans</text></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p91">
    <p>Sextus Empiricus, <text font="italic">Adversus Mathematicos</text> 8.11–12, SVF 2.166:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p92">
    <quote>
      <p>The Stoics say that these three are connected: the
significate (ςημαιν´ομενον), the sign (ςημαι̃νον) and the thing
(τυγχάνον). The sign is the sound itself, e.g. the (sound) ‘Dion’,
the significate is the entity manifested by (this sign) and which we apprehend as co-existing with our thought, (but) which
foreigners do not comprehend, although they hear the sound;
the thing is the external existent, e.g. Dion himself. Of these,
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣375␣**** -->two are bodies, viz. the sound and the thing, and one immaterial,
viz. the entity signified, the <text font="italic">lecton</text>, which (further) is true or false.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p93">
    <p>Peter of Spain, <text font="italic">Tractatus</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="CTMPT" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 79–101]</cite>. “predicable” <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="CTMPT" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 80–81]</cite>:</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p94">
    <quote>
      <p>1. Sometimes ‘predicable’ is used strictly, and in this way only what is predicated of more than one thing is called a predicable. Sometimes it is used broadly, and in this way what is predicated of one or of more than one is called a predicable. Hence, ‘predicable’ taken in its strict sense and ‘universal’ are the same, but
they differ in that a predicable is defined in terms of saying and a universal in terms of being. For a predicable is what is naturally suited to be said of more than one, but a universal is what is
naturally suited to be in more than one.
<break/>
Predicables or universals are divided into genus, differentia, species, proprium, and accident; and our subject here is just these five.</p>
    </quote>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p95">
    <p>predicable: genus, specific difference, species, property, accident.</p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p96">
    <p>Lambert of Auxerre, <text font="italic">Logica</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="CTMPT" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 102–162]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p97">
    <p><text font="italic">Syncategoremata Monacenia</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="CTMPT" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 163–173]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p98">
    <p>Nicholas of Paris, <text font="italic">Syncategoremata</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="CTMPT" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 174–215]</cite>
<!--  %****␣predicates.tex␣Line␣400␣**** --></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p99">
    <p>William of Heytesbury, <text font="italic">De sensu composito et divido</text> <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="CTMPT" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, pp. 413–434]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <para xml:id="p100">
    <p>William of Ockham <cite class="ltx_citemacro_cite">[<bibref bibrefs="grant" separator="," yyseparator=","/>, p. 79]</cite></p>
  </para>
  <bibliography bibstyle="plain" citestyle="numbers" files="predicates" xml:id="bib">
    <title>References</title>
  </bibliography>
</document>
